Professor Dave here, let’s prove the Pythagorean
theorem.
As I mentioned before when we initially learned
the Pythagorean theorem, there are very elegant
ways to prove that the theorem is true, and
now that we know how to calculate area, we
are ready to perform one such proof ourselves.
Let’s say we draw a right triangle like
this one, and label the sides A, B, and C,
like we are used to.
Now let’s make three more copies of this
triangle and arrange them like this, so that
we get two squares.
The larger square has a side length of A plus
B, while the smaller inner square has a side
length of C.
We can calculate the areas of all of these
shapes.
We know that the area of one of the triangles
will be one half base times height, or one
half A times B. The area of the large square
will be the side length squared, or A plus
B quantity squared.
And the small square will have an area of
C squared.
Now let’s set up a relationship between
these areas.
The area of the large square is equal to A
plus B quantity squared as we just said, but
it is also equal to the area of the small
square plus the area of all the triangles,
since these shapes comprise the larger square.
So we can make an equation that states the
following.
A plus B quantity squared, the area of the
big square, is equal to four times one half
AB, which is four times the area of one triangle,
since there are four triangles, plus C squared,
the area of the small square.
We know how to square a binomial by using
the FOIL method, so let’s take away the
exponent and just write the binomial out twice.
First gives us A squared, outer gives us AB,
inner gives us AB, and last gives us B squared.
Combining like terms, that’s A squared plus
two AB plus B squared.
On the right, we can multiply four and one
half, and we get two AB plus C squared.
As it happens, we have two AB on both sides,
so those will cancel out, and wouldn’t you
know it, take a look at what we are left with.
The Pythagorean theorem.
I hope this result makes you feel warm and
fuzzy inside, because proofs like this are
what math is really all about.
There are many other proofs of this theorem
that involve similar calculations with triangles
and squares and other shapes, so if you’re
just dying to know them all, it’s time to
hit the internet.
Otherwise, let’s move forward and wrap things
up with geometry.